<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three severall treatises concerning the truce at this present propounded The first, laying open divers considerations and reasons, why a truce ought not to bee contracted: propounded vnto the high and mightie lords of the States Generall of the Vnited Provinces: by the right honble the commissioners and deputies of the most hon: authorized Company of West India. In their owne behalfe. The second, discusseth this question very pithily and at large, whether or no it bee lawfull to make truce with the King of Spaine, with divers fitting considerations. Lastly, here is added a remonstrance, represented to the States theyr Excellencies, in the behalfe of the King of Bohemia, which hath a respect vnto the affaires in Germanie. All truly and faithfully translated out of the Low Dutch copie.</title>
            <title>Consideratien ende redenen der E. Heeren Bewind-hebberen, vande geoctrojeerde West-Indische Compagnie. English</title>
            <author>West-Indische Compagnie (Netherlands)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13948</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24258</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120731</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855925</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855925</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21433</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13948)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21433)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1011:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three severall treatises concerning the truce at this present propounded The first, laying open divers considerations and reasons, why a truce ought not to bee contracted: propounded vnto the high and mightie lords of the States Generall of the Vnited Provinces: by the right honble the commissioners and deputies of the most hon: authorized Company of West India. In their owne behalfe. The second, discusseth this question very pithily and at large, whether or no it bee lawfull to make truce with the King of Spaine, with divers fitting considerations. Lastly, here is added a remonstrance, represented to the States theyr Excellencies, in the behalfe of the King of Bohemia, which hath a respect vnto the affaires in Germanie. All truly and faithfully translated out of the Low Dutch copie.</title>
                  <title>Consideratien ende redenen der E. Heeren Bewind-hebberen, vande geoctrojeerde West-Indische Compagnie. English</title>
                  <author>West-Indische Compagnie (Netherlands)</author>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Bernard Alsop and Thomas Fawcet] for Nathaniel Butter and Nicholas Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Consideratien ende redenen der E. Heeren Bewind-hebberen, vande geoctrojeerde West-Indische Compagnie.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A" with type ornaments.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Philip --  IV, --  King of Spain, 1605-1665.</term>
               <term>Frederick --  I, --  King of Bohemia, 1596-1632.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21433:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21433:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THREE SEVERALL TREATISES CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CERNING THE TRVCE AT THIS PRESENT propounded.</p>
            <p>The firſt, laying open divers Conſiderations and Reaſons, why a Truce ought not to bee Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted: Propounded vnto the High and Mightie Lords the <hi>States Generall</hi> of the <hi>Vnited Provinces:</hi> By the right Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> the Commiſſioners and Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the moſt Hon: authorized Company of <hi>Weſt India.</hi> In their owne behalfe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, diſcuſſeth this queſtion very pithily and at large, whether or no it bee lawfull to make Truce with the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> with divers fitting Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, here is added a Remonſtrance, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the <hi>States</hi> theyr Excellencies, In the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> which hath a reſpect vnto the Affaires in <hi>Germanie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All truly and faithfully Tranſlated out of the</hi> Low Dutch <hi>Copie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed for <hi>Nathaniel Butter</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Bourne.</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21433:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21433:2"/>
            <head>Three ſeverall Treatiſes concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Truce at this preſent propounded.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <salute>High and Mightie Lords.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough wee aſſure our ſelues and are confident, that your Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Lordſhips both according to your wonted wiſedome can, and according to your ſpeciall benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and favour towards vs, will take into Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; that an eſpeciall duty doth vs all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally bind, both to the conſeruation and increaſing of our Company, and to the ſafetie and welfare of our welbeloued Countrey. Yet neuertheleſſe, wee cannot but eſteeme our ſelues particularly obliged, to ſhew to your Excellencies in all ſubmiſſiue manner briefly, the chiefeſt matters which in this particular are to bee conſidered of.</p>
               <p>1 Firſt, ought to bee taken into conſideration, with what deſire and expectation, the erecting of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany hath both by all good Patriots amongſt our ſelues, as alſo by all welwilling Neighbours and others without our State, been earneſtly looked and hoped for. And how at laſt notwithſtanding much oppoſed, with the Contradictions and gainſtanding of ſome, the ſame though ſlowly is brought to good effect.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21433:3"/>
               <p>Secondly, that your Excellencies out of your owne voluntary motions, haue freely afforded ayde and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to your Subiects And by forme of mutuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, and reciprocall engagement, haue promiſed in caſe of Warre to yeeld them all helpe and furtherance and by Contract with forraigne Nations, to maintaine them in their Corporation.</p>
               <p>3. Thirdly, that hereupon, the Capitall of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, by the inducements of the Directors thereunto appointed by your Excellencies, hath beene wholly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and made compleat, euen by ſuch as your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies your ſelues may iudge and perceiue to ſtand, for the maintainance of the true reformed Religion, &amp; Liberties of our own Country. Inſomuch, that diuers euen from a poore ſtocke, haue largely Contributed.</p>
               <p>4. Fourthly, that by reaſon of this Company, from the firſt beginning, diuers ſhips haue both beene built, and bought, and diuers imployed, which otherwiſe had laine ſtill out of Seruice, for want of Commerce, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique, and employment.</p>
               <p>5. Fifthly, that by this Company, many and great Ships haue beene built, to the manifeſt and apparent encreaſe, of the Nauie and Nauigation. And eſpecially, many faire and ſwift Pinaces.</p>
               <p>6. Sixthly, that the number of our Ships hath from time to time ſo encreaſed, that for the preſent wee can make aboue an hundreth ſayle of very faire well rigged
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21433:3"/> Ships, fit for warlike employment, beeing of ſeuerall bigneſſe, and now at Sea, ready for ſeruice.</p>
               <p>7. Seauenthly, that we haue entertained vpon the ſame Ships a great number both of Marriners and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers continually; ſo that the precedent yeare, we em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in our ſeruice about nine thouſand men, and now at this preſent doe employ neare vpon fifteene thouſand. Now by this meanes our men are wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully trained vp to Nauigation.</p>
               <p>By this meanes are made diuers expert Pilots, and a great number ſo well exerciſed, that our Country may now continually find ſome fit and able men, both to ſerue for Maſter and other inferiour offices in their Nauie.</p>
               <p>8 Eighthly, that we haue victualed the ſame ſhips, ſome for twelue, ſome fifteene, ſome for eighteene, and ſome for more Moneths.</p>
               <p>9. Ninthly, that we haue ſo furniſhed our ſhips with great ſhot, that the laſt yeare wee had in our Nauie 264. braſſe Peeces, among the which were many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miculuerins, and neare vpon 1400. great Falcons; which number this yeare is palpably increaſed ſo that now, wee haue aboue foure hundred braſſe Peeces, and aboue 2000. Falcons, beſides 600. Peeces for ſtone ſhot.</p>
               <p>10. Laſtly, that wee haue prouided and furniſhed the ſame Nauie, with a great quantitie of Powder, which was moſt made heere. So that this laſt yeare, wee haue beſtowed vpon our Nauy, aboue an hundred
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21433:4"/> thouſand pounds of Gunpowder. Out of all which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes doth plainely appeare, what traffique and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our Equipage hath cauſed amongſt vs how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men we haue imployed: With what admirable for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces we haue enriched your Excellencies Nauy. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by great helpe and furtherance is adminiſtred to your Excellencies in time of need and danger. As expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience hath taught of late (without pride be it ſpoken) when our Company ſtood this Country in great ſtead, in their late Broyles and Inconueniencies.</p>
               <p>And now ſtands farther to bee conſidered: What riches and treaſure their Ships haue brought into theſe Countries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt</hi> paſſing by and omitting, whatſoever hath come in former yeares, as Gold, Elephants teeth, Greines, Hides, Skins, Wood, Salt, and the like; (by way of Commerce and Traffique) the Siluer, Coined and Vncoined, which hath beene obtained, by ouercomming the Fleet of <hi>Noua H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſpania,</hi> doth amount to ſuch an infinite treaſure, that neuer the like Prize hath beene brought in, eyther here, or elſewhere.</p>
               <p>Secondly, wee haue theſe late enſuing yeares depriued our Enemies, and enriched our owne Country, with a great deale of <hi>Indigo.</hi> Inſomuch, that towards the latter end of the laſt, and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this yeare, aboue foure thouſand Caſes haue beene brought in.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, a very great quantitie of Sugar; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that this preſent yeare onely hath beene brought in by vs, ſome three thouſand Cheſts.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21433:4"/>
               <p>Fourthly, a wonderfull great number of raw Hides; eſpecially this yeere, aboue ſixe and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thouſands wreſted from the Enemie.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, ſuch a worthy deale of Cochineel, as neuer came in theſe Countries before.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, an vnſpeakable deale of Tobacco, which now is become great Merchandize.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, great riches and treaſure in all manner of coſtly lapida<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſilke, ſilke Wares, Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, all kind of Drugs, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſill Wood, Camperie Wood, and other wares, (which were tedious to relate) ſo that wee haue alreadie brought into theſe Countries many millions. All the which Wares, are bought and diſpearſed amongſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants here; ſome vſed, others tranſported, and howſoeuer thereby are your Excellencies Subiects enriched, the decayed traffique increaſed, and the Convoy ſtrengthened.</p>
               <p>It may ſoone bee perceiued what loſſe our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies haue hereby ſuſtained. Moreouer wee haue ſurpriſed many Galleons from the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which formerly were eſteemed as inuincible Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels; beſides many other Warlike ſhips; paſſing ouer with ſilence, aboue two hundreth ſhips, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Barques Which we haue afforced to our ſelues, appropriated to our owne vſe, &amp; in part deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>The ſame our Ships haue ouermaſtred the rich and mightie Citie S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Salvador</hi> in <hi>Bra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll,</hi> and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed for a while, ranſacked <hi>Portorico,</hi> and explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the way, to command the moſt encloſed Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and haue deſtroyed and demoliſhed the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Saint <hi>Margarita.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:21433:5"/>
               <p>By which manner of doing, wee haue not onely impoueriſhed the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and emptyed his Caſh, but alſo expoſed him to exceſſiue expences.</p>
               <p>Wee ſay, waſted his banckes or Caſh.</p>
               <p>Firſt, withdrawing from him ſo much ſiluer, as ſo much bloud out of a veine.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in diminiſhing his Cuſtome and poundage, as well in <hi>Portugall</hi> as <hi>Spaine.</hi> But hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, eſpecially in <hi>Portugall;</hi> becauſe, there at the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe and returne, thirtie <hi>per Cento</hi> are to be paid.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, alſo in reſpect of the forenamed poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, for want of returne thence, his Subiects are diſanimated and diſcouraged, either to ſhip goods, or ſend ſhips, ſo that the Commerce and Trafique of <hi>Portugall</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> dayly decreaſeth, and their Sugar remaines vpon their hands in extream quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie. In <hi>Braſill</hi> for want of ſhips, and feare of our Nauie, ſo driuen to great charges.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, becauſe we doe hinder the tranſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Blackmoores<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> from the which he doth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiue great Cuſtome, but alſo by them all things are furthered, and ſo he is put to more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, becauſe hee muſt fortifie and ſecure his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy, for whereas he durſt permit his Treaſure to paſſe with 6. 7. or 8. Galleons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hee is compelled to procure thrice as many, and yet dare hardly proceed for feare of our Ships.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, becauſe he was driuen to ſurprize and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the Citie of</hi> Saluador, <hi>with a Nauy of 60 ſayle of Ships, in the which were fifteene thouſand men; Which enterprize, although to ſmall ſucceſſe, coſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21433:5"/> him according to the computation of all diſcreet Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, a hundreth and fiftie tun of treaſure: and yet was ſo fruſtrated, that he got an emptie place, inſtead of a Mountaine, a Mouſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly, becauſe he is forced to entertaine Fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations vpon all his Coaſts and Hauens (for he knowes not where to expect vs) his Gariſons increaſe conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nually, and he ſends amunition continually, and in lieu he did receiue now he deburſeth money, where it commeth to paſſe, that his reuenewes waxe ſmall. And by the way might ſo be oppoſed that he ſhould haue but a ſmall remainder of the ſame. And this alſo might come to paſſe that we might hinder their Spaniſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie of</hi> Terra firma, Hondacus, <hi>and</hi> Noua Hiſpania, <hi>From arriuing in their due and appointed time, and from wintering in their deſired ports (as lately hath beene experienced by our Fleet, vnder the command of the Admirall</hi> Adriaem I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſs. Pater) <hi>to their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſsible expences and dangerous paſſage, in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accuſtomed ſeaſon, ſo that his enterprize may be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether fruſtrated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Out of all which appeares, that the Kings Cheſts are emptie, that his credit failes, and all his adhae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents are forced to breake, and ſtoope low, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners here are vnſatisfied; inſomuch, that euery one that lookes with an indifferent eye, may perceiue that this our <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Companie hath afforded the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> an irreparable oppoſition and damage, and is like to make this breach greater, if her proceedings be but continued, and ſeaſonably ſeconded.</p>
               <p>Vnto which premiſſes ſerue theſe ſubſequent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21433:6"/> which neuer yet were incident, nor euer are like to be; to wit, that diuers of his Countries of greateſt importance are ſore diuided. For the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>on is among the <hi>Spaniards</hi> themſelues, and there is no ſmall jealouſie among the <hi>Negroes</hi> and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtered <hi>Barbarians.</hi> Vnto which inconueniences, he cannot adminiſter a remedie, by reaſon of the want of money, yet he wants the beneuolence of all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n there. Which iumpe of occaſion we can wait on, and beat him at his owne weapons.</p>
               <p>We haue now alſo by our owne loſſe, and at our owne coſt learned this ſlight, to touch him boldeſt where hee is weakeſt. If now the current of this our ſtreame ſhould bee ſtopped, hee will recouer his ſtrength, and reſtore all things to a new forme vnknowne to vs.</p>
               <p>Wee will not expect now that your Excellen: will hereafter, eyther ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght or forget the ſeruice of our Company performed for our Countryes. For otherwiſe as we haue declared and propounded to your Excel: the benefit and commodity. Which this Country hath enioyed by the proceeding and good ſucceſſe of our Companie: ſo could we like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe make knowne vnto your Excellen: diuers moſt euident dammages and loſſes which wee are like to ſuſtaine, and conſequently would enſue, if the kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of this vnited Companie ſhould once bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyed. For as the ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fit of this worke hath beene great in the ſucceſſe, which wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke we haue brought to perfection with exceſſiue charges, with great ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard and danger; ſo all the world may ſoone per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, and all men doe alreadie foreſee, that if the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21433:6"/> ſtrength and power of this company ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by the diſſoluing of the ſame, there would ineuitably follow the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ct contrarie, vnto what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer wee haue de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ucted for the proſperitie of theſe Countries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As firſt. Wee ſhall not bee able to employ our ſhips, and therefore he conſtrained to ſell and put off many of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nay the moſt part at ſmall vnder rates: build no more, hyre no more but whereas now and than, ſome falſe knaue or other, doth ſecretly conuey ſome ſhip furniture, amunition, or ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p vnto the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wee ſhould ſee our beſt ſhips fitteſt for War, and Nauigation, tranſported th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther before euery mans eyes, without feare or parting backe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, Wee ſhould not bee able to yeeld ſeruice and employment to our Mariners, which would cauſe them to flye to the Enemy, and tender him their ſeruice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly, it is to be feared that the ſame our ſea-men hauing taſted the ſweetneſſe of our bootie and Prizes would betake themſelues to Pyrates, and ſo ouer throw the ſafety of our Nauigation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly, that (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the former Truce) men will ſtudy and end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>auour to ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with leſſe charges, and ſo own ſhot and amunit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on, or at leaſtw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe take that which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſlight and of no value, and ſo in time of need and common danger, we<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall bee to ſeeke, and found vnprouided.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not procure ſuch abundance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> into our Countries, or at leaſtwiſe not ſo che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and at ſo ſmall charges, conſidering that all muſt paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnder the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eauie burden of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21433:7"/> Toll and Cuſtome, ſo that the Creame wil be skimmed off before the milke come to our hands, whence muſt of neceſſitie enſue a decreaſe in Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and all manner of Trafique.</p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe, the K. of <hi>Spaine</hi> ſhall by this meanes obtaine and recouer his Gold &amp; Siluer ſprings and veynes at liberty, get forward againe, waxe ſtrong, redreſſe and rectifie the great diſorder in yonder parts. Reedifie his decayed Fortreſſes, build new, in ſtead that now he findes them laid open. He will alſo then eyther allure the Sauages to himſelfe, or otherwiſe extirpate them, who now doe much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to vs, In a word, he wil ſo reeſtabliſh all things there, that it will bee in vaine for vs to endeauour that way in future time.</p>
               <p>That all this is truth, wee ſhall need no other wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to teſtifie, then common voyces, for the moſt part euen of thoſe that are afarre off, or of your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies ſubiects, who doe vnanimouſly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that they haue euer been of that opinion, that nothing can be enterprized more preiudicial to our common Enemy, then to aſſault him in thoſe parts, whence he doth obtaine with what hee doth curbe all Chriſtendome, and whereby he hath now many yeares aſpired to the vniuerſall Monarchy. And that therefore according to the beginnings, they doe perceiue themſelues not deceiued in their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and judgement. Wee doe appeale to our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy himſelfe, who cannot Conceale that there is nothing preſſeth them ſo ſore, nor vrgeth more to deſire a Truce then the weapons of our Company and that if this Thorne were but out of their foot,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21433:7"/> they will then giue vs what-ſoeuer advantage.</p>
               <p>Inſomuch then, the Intreſt of a common harme is greater then that of particular copartners, who (as they ſay concerning the moſt part) haue aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured their monies more for loue, then greedineſſe of gaine, they could eaſily endure that loſſe which ſhould befall them by the diſſolution of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, if thereby the common good and publicke weale were furthered. Becauſe by this meanes the party will recouer his ſtrength, take breath, get new blood and vigonr, and to the contrary theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries will decay and faint, and ſtraine one of their beſt points, and (if we might be ſo bold to ſay) lame an arme.</p>
               <p>Alſo it might come to paſſe, that this buſineſſe might be vndertaken by ſome other, and wee ſtand and be ſpectators onely, and ſo neuer come to bee our ſelues againe in this matter. The moſt we might expect ſhould bee a Competencie, and Dependan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie on others.</p>
               <p>In Concluſion then. Wee doe moſt ſubmiſſiuely requeſt and intreat, that your Excel: (according to your wonted wiſedome) would bee pleaſed to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent theſe forenamed Inconueniencies and loſſes: and not ſuffer our Companie (as we haue deducted before) to be ruinated by a Truce, and the <hi>Spaniard</hi> to take breath and gather ſtrength. But rather that it would pleaſe) our Excellen: to maintayne our Company in their former right, &amp; incourage, and ſtrengthen them in their good purpoſe and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to ſuffer them to inioy &amp; reape the fruits of ſo many dangers, hazards, paines and troubles
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21433:8"/> as their Capitals and Services haue vndergone and ſuſtained, and the good reſpect which they haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrued from this State. Not ſhuffing and putting fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that great bleſſing which the Lord hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to beſtow vpon their Countries, by the meanes of this Company.</p>
               <p>And ſo wee truſt that the ſame bleſſing will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue amongſt vs, to the propagation of his name, and honour and inlighting of our owne Countrey. Vnto the which, according to out meane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours we are and will be ſtill willing to Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute. And will alwayes bee ready to declare fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſons of this our backwardneſſe to your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies, and will euer remaine, &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Excellencies, moſt humble Servants. <hi>The Deputies of the authorized</hi> Weſt India <hi>Companie. At their Meeting the</hi> 19. Was thus Subſcribed.
<list>
                        <item>REYNIER REAEL.</item>
                        <item>IOHAN DE ZAET.</item>
                        <item>A PIETERSONS.</item>
                        <item>SYMON VERDOES.</item>
                        <item>DIDRICH SCHERF.</item>
                        <item>ALBERT WYFFERINCK.</item>
                        <item>ANTHONY GODU<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</item>
                        <item>MARCVS VAN VALI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KENBVRCH</item>
                        <item>GERRIT. VAN NYBVRG<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</item>
                        <item>IOHAN DE MOOR.</item>
                        <item>ABRAHAM OYENS.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21433:8"/>
               <head>Diuers Conſcionable Conſiderations vpon this Queſtion: <hi>Whether in Conſcience men may contract a Truce with the King of</hi> Spaine.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore any thing bee vndertaken, it is neceſſary, that in the firſt place this queſtion be made, Whether or no it be agreeable to Gods moſt holy will, &amp; may be performed with a ſafe conſcience.</p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> of bleſſed and happy memory, When as there was to bee treated at <hi>Bourborgh</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> concerning a Peace with the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> aſwell in the behalfe of the the Queene of <hi>England,</hi> as on the behalfe of theſe Countries, did then chiefly pauſe vpon this point, and to this end called together an Aſſembly or Synode of Clergie men, to conſult of that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. It were very requiſire that our high and mighty Superiours followed the ſame ſteps, and in this Treaty of Truce, did conſult with the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God, and ſo take Counſell from his owne Word. But notwithſtanding this is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely at this time, yet will not theſe few conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations proue vnneceſſary and vnprofitable, euen to the ſatisfying and informing the conſciences of thoſe who ſhal hereafter read and peruſe them. My deſire therefore is, that they may bee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and thought vpon, with vnfaigned loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, in his feare, and for his Truths ſake.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:21433:9"/>
               <p>The Queſtion here is not, Whether or no wee may with a ſafe Conſcience make war againſt the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and while he continues war, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed and continue ours againſt him. Wee hold this affirmatiue, and lay it as a ground of truth: For we know that true Maxime receiued of all true Chriſtians, and the higher Powers of theſe Countries, and indeed is grounded vpon the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures, That <hi>the Magiſtrates doe not beare the Sword in vaine;</hi> but for the ſuppreſſing and puniſhing of the bad, and for the defence of the good; for the good of their Subjects; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, not only againſt priuate offenders, who haue damaged and wronged this and that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſon, but alſo againſt generall and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke offenders, who labour to diſturbe and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the ſtate of the Land, and the Publicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale: But the Queſtion is this, Whether or no we may ceaſe making warre; or (to be plainer) Whether wee may for a time, or for certaine yeeres, ſhut vp and ſtop our proceedings in warre.</p>
               <p>This Queſtion being thus propounded in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in the <hi>Theſis</hi> or Poſition, it vnfolds it ſelfe: For who dares doubt but wee may ceaſe warring with mutual agreement, when the contrary party either requireth, or is willing to doe the ſame? Therefore the Queſtion propounded in the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> is without difficulty, except it be among ſuch as either are blood-thirſty, or reuengefull, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend either to enrich or aduance themſelues by the booty and prey; ſuch I meane, as would not deale in this matter according to conſcience, but their owne beaſtly and fleſhly luſts.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:21433:9"/>
               <p>Here lyes the point in the <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> or condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Propoſition: that is, when this Queſtion is applyed to our common Enemy, and his ſtate and condition; whether then it may conſiſt with ſafety of Conſcience to contract a Truce with the King of <hi>Sptine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here two things offer themſelues to bee conſidered:</p>
               <p>Firſt, the Condition of the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, our ſtate and preſent condition, and occaſions.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, it is certaine, and beyond doubt, that the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> our enemy, doth not now enter into Treatie with vs concerning a Truce, either out of loue to peace, or loue to our perſons.</p>
               <p>This is manifeſt and euident in the proceedings of all his warres from time to time, alſo in his warres continued againſt vs. It doth appeare that he aymes onely to erect his ſuppoſed and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vniuerſall Monarchie, and abſolute Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Remember the warres, whereby he did help the Emperour, for the ſuppreſſing and ſubduing of thoſe that were vnited with vs in religion and loue, euen while he entertained a Truce with vs. Conſider the wars which he euen now vndergo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in <hi>Italy</hi> againſt the French King, &amp; other parts of the world; and will treate with vs, not concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Peace, but a Truce. He eſteemes vs his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, he hates vs as ſuch, wherefore he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer acknowledge vs for free Countries, nor neuer will as long as the World ſtands. He onely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles, and conceales his malice for a while, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a better and fitter opportunity. How hee
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21433:10"/> hath continued in his hatred and malice againſt vs, hath ſufficiently beene manifeſted ſince our Truce with him hath been expired. What moues him then, and induceth him to this? Nothing but his loue to his owne State, and preſuppoſed and imaginary vniuerſall Monarchy. For ſeeing that it is impoſſible for him to attaine to that height, through his warres againſt vs, and that God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords vs in our proceedings of Warre, ſufficient meanes, to confirme our State, and debilitate his; hee labours by his Truce to wreſt the meanes out of our hands; and ſo to fortifie and confirme his State againſt ours, to the end that hee may with more eaſe and profitable ſucceſſe, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of our loſſe, recollect himſelfe, and make his war the ſtronger.</p>
               <p>If any one oppoſe thus; How-euer things are, yet in the time of Truce wee ſhall poſſeſſe and enioy reſt and tranquility, without Warre and combuſtion; then ought this to bee conſidered of;</p>
               <p>Whether or no this can vndoubtedly bee affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. For if wee can bee aſſured of reſt and peace, what neede ſo many Souldiers bee kept in ſeruice, laid in Garriſon vpon all the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers? Why doe wee not ſaue theſe Charges, and decreaſe our coſt? Hence appeares then, that wee cannot bee ſecure, and certaine of the fidelity of our Enemy, or of any reſt and peace, euen in time of the Truce.</p>
               <p>This muſt needes be ſo; for we deale with an Enemie, who neither ſtands to his word nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21433:10"/> although confirmed with his owne hand, ſeale, and Oath.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Maximes of your Popiſh Counſels, that no faith is to bee kept with Heretickes, is knowne throughout the whole World, and the practiſe of the ſame is made manifeſt in all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. Theſe <hi>Netherlands</hi> haue by wofull expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience tryed and taſted of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> infidelity: doe but reade thoſe paſſages that are paſt, turne ouer our Hiſtories, and they will abundantly teſtifie the ſame.</p>
               <p>Shall wee ſay that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> is by former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience better taught, and is now of another mind and condition? Who ſhall aſſure vs of this? It cannot ſo ſoone bee ſaid, but may as ſoone bee denyed. And the Negatiue is more probable then the Affirmatiue. For this you muſt grant, that hee is ſtill bound in conſcience to the Pope of <hi>Rome;</hi> and you know that he aſcribes to himſelfe this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that hee can and will free the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of men, from their obligation by Oath, that hee can diſcharge Subiects from their Oath of Allegiance, made to their Prince and Superiours; that hee hath power to ſtirre vp and incenſe Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects againſt their Kings and Magiſtrates, to depoſe Kings, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>When now the Pope ſhall ſee this to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and prooue beneficiall to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> will hee not farre rather haue the power to free the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> from his promiſe made eyther by ſubſcription or Oath, to ſuch which he holds for Hereticks and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Subiects?</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:21433:11"/>
               <p>Nay, will he not rather ordaine that for the good &amp; benefit of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> doe vnawares and ſuddenly intercept, and fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon them. Shall we ſay, this can be preuented, by entertaining and keeping our Weapons, guarding our frontiers, and being vigilant that they doe not ſuddenly fall on vs, and ſo keepe him from his enterprize, and be out of danger? What then will the Truce ſignifie? which we ſhall be faine to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine in lieu of a defenſiue warre? and in the meane while barring our ſelues from all opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of aduantaging our ſelues againſt our enemie?</p>
               <p>Concerning the ſecond point, namely our ſtate and preſent occaſion: The Lords the States of theſe Countries doe profeſſe to maintaine the true refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Chriſtian Religion; Thus they declare in their ordaining of their Faſts, they ſhew in their Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations to Kings, Princes, and States, they pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the ſame in their Proclamations and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and they doe well; ſo that one of the chiefeſt Maximes of our State, is the managing of the true Chriſtian Religion. Now let vs examine whether the Truce is intended to that end; 'tis certaine that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> doth hate vs for nothing more, and for no other cauſe but this Religion; he alſo vſeth the ſame for a pretenſe to iuſtifie his warres againſt vs, and to declare and ſhew that we haue forfeited our Priuiledges.</p>
               <p>He perceiues now, that he cannot attaine vnto all this by open Warre, he therefore labours to bring it to paſſe by the Truce. And in very deed hee can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> no better meanes: For he knowes how many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ctaries here are amongſt vs, all enemies to the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21433:11"/> ſame Religion, how many inhabitants in theſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries yet cleane and adhere to Popery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> how the Prieſts and Ieſuites ſwarme here, ayming and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuouring to incenſe the hearts of the Subiects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our State and Religion: nay more, euen to ſeduce and envelop the very hearts of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Gouernours. Conſider againe, that two ſorts of people chiefly doe bend and oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt our State and Religion; the Papiſts, and Remonſtrants; the Papiſts pleading and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that the Sate of theſe Countries is an vſurped State, and that the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> is lawfull Heyre of theſe Countries. The Remonſtrants, becauſe their deſigne and purpoſe is diſmiſſed, and their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction repreſſed, euen out of a bitter hatred and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt the Religion and gouernment of theſe Countries, expreſſing themſelues moſt vilely and violently, yea many times vttering theſe and the like ſpeeches, <hi>That they doe acknowledge the King of</hi> Spaine <hi>to be the natural Lord of theſe Countries.</hi> Now he knowes how the other Sectaries doe vphold and animate theſe two ſorts of people, and that conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the true Religion hath as many internall as externall enemies. And that theſe youthes are now compelled to be ſtill, or at leaſt cannot ſo well and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly lift vp their heads in time of war as they would doe in time of truce. Experience hath ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently taught in the former Truce, how they did endeauour and ſtriue to ſuppreſſe the Religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, what power and ſubtilty thereunto hath beene vſed, how thoſe factious people and enemies of true Religion, did all at once eleuate and beſtirre themſelues, to worke out their malice and hatred
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21433:12"/> againſt the Religion. And had not the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wonderfully prouided for vs, in what wofull e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate had we found our ſelues? Hence it comes to paſſe that thoſe that were vnited vnto vs in the ſame Religion, were in the former Truce thus miſerably and earneſtly perſecuted in <hi>Germany,</hi> and wofully ſubdued. This is an vndoubted truth, if our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be loſt, our Countries are loſt: now, how neere it was come to this point with our Religion, in the former Truce, cannot but be palpable, to him who is either of vnderſtanding or iudgement.</p>
               <p>Who doubts, but this proffer of Truce tends to the ſame ſcope? Now that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> hates the Religion, and therfore imployes all meanes, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects all his actions to extirpate the ſame, is without and beyond diſpute. That all Sectaries within theſe Countries hate Religion, and do but wait for an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to expell the ſame, needs no proofe. The <hi>Spaniard</hi> he propounds a Truce, all the Papiſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, all Sectaries, Remonſtrants, Baſtad-Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therians, Anabaptiſts, people without any religion, and ſuch we call Libertines, commend it, call for it, are ready to embrace it. Now conſider whether this Truce can poſſibly ſerue for the managing, maintenance and defence of the fore-named true Religion. The <hi>Spaniard</hi> expects and hopes that the Sectaries will lift vp their heads, and take an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to ſuppreſſe this Region. The Sectaries they long and deſire to obtaine ſuch an opportunity: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially that knowne and noted Faction, who doe trauell, as it were, in labour, with a bitter hatred, till they can by ſuch an oportunity reuenge themſelues. This it is that cauſeth all faithfull Patriots, and true
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21433:12"/> louers of the fore-named Religion, to bee ſenſible of the danger, &amp; to apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of this Truce ſo grieuouſly.</p>
               <p>Now let it be duely pondered in the feare of GOD, whether it may conſiſt with a ſafe conſcience, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the Countries, to be deceiued, and ſuddenly and vnexpectedly to be ſurprized of our enemy; to giue into the hands of our enemies, thoſe meanes which they themſelues deeme and iudge to ſerue for the reſtauration of their State, and weakning of ours. To yeeld an opportunity to our externall and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall enemies, which they deſire and long for, euen to the end they may ſuppreſſe the true Religion: To for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake and abandon thoſe that are vnited with vs in the true Religion, in <hi>Germany</hi> and elſe-where, and caſt off ſuch meanes as God hath yeelded vnto vs for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution: To grieue our Friends, ioy and animate our enemies, and all this at ſuch a time, when <hi>God</hi> doth palpably bleſſe vs, doth eſtabliſh our State, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found our enemies; and ſo vngratefully reiect Gods mercies and bleſſings, and trample them vnder our feet. Theſe conſiderations ought we to take to heart, for no reaſons with any ground can preuaile againſt them, vnleſſe we could afore-hand be aſſured, that the Truce is required, with loue to the welfare of theſe Countries, and that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> will firmly keep his word: And that by Generall Councell, with conſent and approbation of the Pope, that Decree ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked, That no faith is to be kept with Heretickes; and vnleſſe he doe reſigne the power of diſpenſing with Oathes. That alſo the Sectaries ſhall bee quiet and ſtill, without turbulency, or endeuouring to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Religion; and that all Gouernours, aſwell in generall as particular, ſhall vnanimouſly, with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21433:13"/> and integrity, labour and ſtriue to maintaine and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rther the reformed Religion. For as long as we haue not this aſſurance, the former conſiderations re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in full force.</p>
               <p>If queſtion be made, what aſſurance we haue againſt this in time of warre, the anſwer is at hand. Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (we know) teacheth vs, that thoſe Armes, which through Gods bleſſing we beare againſt our enemies, as it is confeſt, in time of Truce we muſt ſtill beare for farther aſſurance: and whereas by reaſon of war we are as it were vnited and ioyned together, ſo that we ſhall not, like vnto looſe brooms, fall aſunder: whence will come to paſſe, that thoſe that are enemies to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſhall not haue opportunity to put in practiſe their malicious enterprizes.</p>
               <p>The principall thing that can heere be obiected in caſe of conſcience, is, that war is a cruell beaſt, and this beaſt will reſt at leaſt-wiſe in time of Truce. But in this caſe conſider, how much the more furious and cruell ſhe will be, after ſhe ſhall be rouzed out of her ſleepe, and how this hath bin already experienced by thoſe grand Armies which the Enemy did produce after the laſt Truce, as alſo his power at Sea. This is a lamentable thing, and a matter of conſcience, when ſo much blood is ſpilt: But what will it be, when the Enemy, by reaſon of the Truce, ſhall, hauing recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his ſtrength, deuoure vs and our children, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his tyranous and bloody nature, and cruell diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition? Shall we then thinke no humane blood bee ſpilt? And to what end I pray' tends the Truce, but to this deſigne? When the internall enemies of the Countries, vnto true Religion, ſhall oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt the defenders and profeſſors of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21433:13"/> and then theſe ſuppoſe themſelues to haue iuſt cauſe to defend them, ſhall within our ſelues fall toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the eares? Will not this be a wofull ſpectacle for vs, and pleaſing vnto them our enemies? Oh how neere was it come to this puſh by the former Truce? and had preuailed, if God had not wonderfully proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Was it not come to the very height of this ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle.</p>
               <p>But who are thoſe that ſpeake in this wiſe? are they not Papiſts, whoſe qualities we cannot be vnacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with? who, as long as the Armes in theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries take good ſucceſſe, they make a faire ſhew of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on our ſide; but as ſoone as euer the caſe doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they cannot conceale their villanous malice. Did it not lately appeare, when the enemy was in the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lewe,</hi> and when <hi>Amersfort</hi> was loſt?</p>
               <p>Are they not Remonſtrants, whoſe partiall mindes and intentions doe manifeſt themſelues in all their ſpeeches, writings, and actions? Are they not other Sectaries, who all alike are linked together, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the true Religion, the ſafety and glory of our State? Notwithſtanding they make a faire ſhew of Peace, and ſparing of humane blood, 'tis to ſpare the Enemy, and fauour them, and to ſuppreſſe the true Patriots of the Countreys. This is <hi>Sauls</hi> mercie to <hi>Agag</hi> the King of the <hi>Amalechites,</hi> who in the mean while vſed all diligence to deſtroy the vpright King <hi>Dauid. Achab</hi> the King or <hi>Iſrael</hi> fauoured <hi>Benhadad</hi> the King of <hi>Syria,</hi> when he beeing in the vtmoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, truſted to this, that the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were mercifull Kings.</p>
               <p>Such mercy did the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhew vnto the Idolatrous Kings, enemies vnto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21433:14"/> they for their parts, cruelly perſecuted the Prophets of the Lord, becauſe they did not ſpeake pleaſing to their palates. This is the quality of all Hypocrites, and enemies of true Religion; they cry all for mercie, when as wee haue to doe with Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and enemies of God and his Church: But when they haue to doe with the faithfull ſeruants of God, protectors of his true Religion, then they haue aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned and caſt off all mercie. Lay downe therefore this ſiniſter mercie, leſt that puniſhment which was threatned and befell the mercifull Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall you alſo. Shew your mercy to the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, who are perſecuted by the Idolater and falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhippers: Looke vpon God, and the iuſtice of our Cauſe: Labour to further Gods Honour, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the true Religion, to protect our owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie againſt our Common ſworne Enemy. Doe this in holy zeale, in Gods feare, with a confident bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Courage; and the Lord of Hoſts bee with you.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21433:14"/>
               <head>Remonſtrance To be ſhewed and preſented, in behalfe of the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> vnto the High and Mighty Lords, the Lords the States Generall of the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Low-Countrie Prouinces.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>Concerning this preſent Treatie of ceaſing Armes, or Truce.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>High and Mighty Lords:</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WHereas it hath pleaſed Almighty GOD to giue ſo good a ſucceſſe vnto the wars of the high &amp; mighty Lords the States of the Vnited Prouinces, aſwell by Sea as by Land, ſo that the Enemy finding himſelfe in great extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, is conſtrained to ſeeke after a Truce and ceaſing of Armes, thereby to breathe himſelfe: His Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> who alſo is partaker of this happines, and herein doth congratulate your Excellencies, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but (through and for the inſeparable loue, which from old time hath bin between His Maieſties Houſe, and is yet maintained in this State, as alſo in reſpect of the common intereſt) earneſtly intreate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt your Excellencies, that in caſe they ſhould finde and deeme it neceſſary, profitable, and for the beſt of their Prouinces, to aſſent vnto a Treaty of Truce: That they would be pleaſed not to draw a concluſion, vnleſſe the reſtitution of his Maieſtie bee therein ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely ſet downe, agreed, and comprehended.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21433:15"/>
               <p>Conſidering, firſt, that theſe vnited Prouinces can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not promiſe to themſelues, much leſſe expect any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, reſt, or peace, as long as <hi>Germany,</hi> and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> doe remaine vnder the ſuppreſſion of the Houſe of <hi>Austria,</hi> and <hi>Spaine:</hi> Conſidering that by how much more the forementioned Houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria</hi> ſhall hence-forward chance to eleuate and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh her fortune and dignity, in the ruine, loſſe, and deſtruction of the moſt Illuſtrious Houſes and kindred of <hi>Germany;</hi> and aboue all, of the <hi>Prince Elector Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine;</hi> by ſo much the more, meanes and opportunitie will be yeelded vnto them, for the ioyning of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces together of the whole body of the Empire, and for the bending of all their power againſt the State of theſe Countries, in all accidentall occaſions whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, being proffered and preſented vnto them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking notice of any treaty or agreement. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſecondly, to the contrary, the forementioned houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> with their adherents, (who hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, by their vniuſt and ouerchargeable procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, haue ſtirred againſt them the diſpleaſure and ill will of all the Euangelicall Princes of the Empire) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin now to feare ſome euill euent, and fearfull alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, diſturbance, and ſubuerſion in their affaires. which feare is much accrewed, through the euident and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Victories of the high and mighty Lords the States generall of theſe Vnited Prouinces.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, this being very euident and apparant, that the malice and hatred that the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> doe beare to the Houſe of the Prince Elector <hi>Palatine,</hi> principally doth hence proceed, Becauſe the ſame Houſe hath euer beene well addicted and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, and hath euer as much as in her lay, furthered
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21433:15"/> and fauoured the welfare, profit &amp; increaſe of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer did concerne the State of theſe Low-Countries. For which cauſes, the Emperour formerly hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and declared vnto the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> in his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, dated the 14. of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1621. (which Letters are now in the hands of his Maieſty of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and are truely the very originall Letters) that this State of the Vnited Prouinces can neuer be brought vnder the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and power of <hi>Spaine,</hi> as long as the Houſe of the Elector <hi>Palatine</hi> is not wholly extirpated, and cut off from the Empire.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, May it pleaſe your Excellencies, the high and mighty States generall, to be mindfull, that the Articles of the forbearance, which they contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the King of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> the 7 of <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1625. doe comprehend the Palatinate, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer concernes the ſame, confirmed with very power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and expreſſe words and termes againſt the Houſe of <hi>Spaine</hi> and her adherents. His Maieſtie confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repoſing, that your Excellencies would carefully be mindfull of all this, and take into conſideration the faithfull Seruices, which his Maieſties Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, as namely his Father and Grandfathers, haue done vnto this State.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, this alſo is to be held for a certaine, that if the <hi>Palatinate</hi> be wholly excluded in this Treaty of a Truce, which is now propounded and proffered vnto your Excellencies, this would inforce an irreparable loſſe and hinderance to the reſtitution of his Maieſty, and conſequently to all the affaires of whole <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> which haue their relation and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lexe vnto the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Prouinces. But aboue all &amp; in concluſion, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is not only handled the particular of his Maieſty,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21433:16"/> but alſo the repairing, as alſo the liberty and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="7 letters">
                     <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the reformed Churches, which at this day ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y groane vnder the burden and yoake of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> and the which doe inceſſantly and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> intreat the Lord for the welfare and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of theſe vnited Prouinces. Inſomuch, that whatſoeuer your Excellencies ſhall doe in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, will ſerue much for the magnifying of Gods glory, and (which is the onely ſcope or marke to which all our actions ought to bee directed) to the refreſhing and eaſing of many oppreſſed and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed hearts; and hereby allure Gods bleſſing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Countries, and gaine immortall praiſe to your Excellencies, and more and more increaſe the obliegement of His Maieſtie and his Succeſſors to your Excellencies. And your Excellencies may be aſſured, that His Maieſtie and His, being reſtored to the Inheritance of their Fathers, ſhall euer bee carefull to tender your Excellencies all bounden dutie and ſeruice of ſincere loue, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting acknowledgment, as often as time, meanes, and opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhall be afforded.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21433:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
